John Cohen collection, circa 1939-2019
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
John Cohen collection circa 1939-2019
AFC 2011/059
Cohen, John, 1932-2019
approximately 32,630 items
37 linear feet
83 containers; 17,300 sheets
121 photographs: film negatives, black-and-white and color; 35 mm
approximately 1750 photographic prints: black-and-white and color
1,271 photographs: digital, TIFF files
70 posters: black-and-white and color; 24 x 33 in. and smaller
379 paintings and drawings: black-and-white and color; 22.5 x 28 in. and smaller
10 oil paintings, watercolor and mixed media pieces: color; 15 x 18 in. and smaller
223 sound cassettes: analog
107 sound wire reels: analog
575 sound tape reels (5 in., 7in., 10 in.): analog
456 sound discs: analog, 45 rpm; 7 in.
34 sound discs (CD-R): optical; 4 3/4 in.
20 sound discs (DVD-R): optical; 4 3/4 in.
11 floppy disks: digital; 3 1/2 in.
43 floppy disks: digital; 5 1/4 in.
922 text and image files from CD-R, DVD-R, floppy disks: digital
1 hard drive with 7,520 moving image, audio, still image files: digital
approximately 1800 film elements in 900 containers from 16 finished films
16 films reels: color; 16 mm
1 banjo; 5 string
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of manuscripts, sound recordings, graphic images, and moving images created and collected by John Cohen. The materials document Cohen's parallel careers as a musician (member of the New Lost City Ramblers) and writer during the 1960s American folk music revival, and his celebrated work as a documentary photographer and filmmaker, producer, and artist from the 1950s to the present. Includes interviews made by Cohen with John Hartford, Harry Smith, Roger McGuinn, Pete Seeger, Bob Dylan, Gary Davis, John Summers, Cousin Emmy, Roscoe Holcomb, Charlie Higgins, Wade Ward, Friends of Old Time Music, High Atmosphere, and photographs of these and others including E. C. Ball, Clancy Brothers, Elizabeth Cotten, Willie Dixon, Jack Elliott, Woody Guthrie, Mary Frank, Lilly Brothers, Alan Lomax, Bill Monroe, Earl Scruggs, Mike Seeger, Stanley Brothers, Belle Stewart, Stony Mountain Boys, Merle Travis, Muddy Waters, Doc Watson and many others. The collection includes documentation of Greenwich Village and Harlem, New York City; Cohen's travels to Paris and Spain in the 1950s; and later to England, Wales, Scotland, Germany, Italy and Japan, and other countries. Notable is his research for his master's thesis on Peruvian textile weaving, and subsequent fieldwork in Peru. Subsequent projects in Peru incorporated sound recordings of Andean music, and films as well as books about weaving, music, festivals, and dance. The majority of Cohen's Peru photographs were taken during his first three trips there and focus primarily on indigenous Andean people in the Q'ero region.
Provenance
John Cohen, Purchase; 2011.
Reid Cramer, Gift; 2020, 2021.
Custodial History
Materials in this collection were in the possession of John Cohen and his family until their donation to the American Folklife Center.
Accruals
Original acquisition received in 2011; Additional accruals received in January 2020 and August 2021; Additional accrual expected in 2022/2023.
Related Material
John Cohen interview conducted by Todd Harvey and David Quick, 2012 March 26 [videorecording] (AFC 2012/011)
John Cohen and Penny Seeger collection of Peru recordings (AFC 1972/005)
Mike Cohen and John Cohen wire recordings (AFC 1980/003)
John Cohen folk music of Kentucky collection (AFC 1960/006)
'The High lonesome sound' revisited: documenting traditional culture in America, 2009 June 11 / lecture by John Cohen; sponsored by the American Folklife Center (AFC 2009/010) and the webcast.
John and Ginny Dildine collection (AFC 1975/001). Includes recording from May 25, 1958 of the first time John Cohen, Mike Seeger, and Tom Paley played together on the radio (they went on to become the New Lost City Ramblers) (AFC 1975/001: SR013)
John Cohen's photography is held by various institutions, including the Brooklyn Museum; Detroit Institute of Arts; Metropolitan Museum of Art; Morgan Library and Museum; Museum of Fine Arts in Houston, TX; Museum of Modern Art; Nasher Museum of Art; Duke University; National Gallery of Art; National Portrait Gallery; Neuberger Museum; New York Public Library; Victoria and Albert Museum; and Yale University Art Gallery.
Access and Restrictions
The John Cohen collection is open to research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
John Cohen was born in 1932 in Queens, New York, to Russian Jewish parents, Israel Cohen and Sonya (Shack) Cohen, and raised on Long Island. Cohen earned a bachelor of fine arts (1951) and completed a master of fine arts (1957), both from Yale University. As an undergraduate, Cohen studied painting with artist and educator, Josef Albers, but shifted his focus to photography after being exposed to Robert Frank's documentary photography work. He studied with modernist photographer Herbert Matter, who Cohen assisted on a project documenting performances of gospel music in Harlem. Cohen's deepening artistic sense, combined with learning about weaving customs of Peru through an archeology course, would lead him to travel to the Peruvian Andes, write his master's thesis on their weaving customs, and commence his lifelong involvement documenting Andean communities.
Cohen was also an active musician. While at Yale, he organized music festivals and continued his work presenting concerts later in New York City during the emergence of the folk revival. In 1958, Cohen founded the New Lost City Ramblers, along with Mike Seeger and Tom Paley (replaced by Tracy Schwarz in 1962). The New Lost City Ramblers was an old time string band that embraced a respect for rural Appalachian traditions and canons, while infusing originality and making the music accessible to folk revival audiences in New York City and throughout the United States. The band created more than 20 albums together.
While living in New York City during the late 1950s, Cohen became involved with the Avant Garde and Abstract Expressionist art world. Robert Frank, Cohen's next door neighbor, enlisted Cohen as still photographer of Pull My Daisy, the influential Beat Generation film directed by Frank, written by Jack Kerouac, and featuring Allen Ginsberg, Peter Orlovsky, Gregory Corso, David Amram, and others. In addition to documenting the artistic Avant Garde art and literary world of his New York neighborhood, Cohen photographed significant folk musicians, such as Woody Guthrie and a young Bob Dylan. He was a founding director of the Friends of Old Time Music, a group including Ralph Rinzler and Izzy Young, which presented 14 concerts of traditional musicians to New York audiences for the first time. Performers included Roscoe Holcomb, the Stanley Brothers, Maybelle Carter, Doc Watson, Mississippi John Hurt, and Dock Boggs. In addition to using his musical and personal connections for booking artists, John did the artwork and design for posters and fliers for many of the concerts.
In 1965, Cohen married Penelope (Penny) Seeger (1943-1993), daughter of the well-known musicians and musicologists Ruth Crawford Seeger and Charles Seeger. Penny was a singer and musician, as were her siblings, Barbara, Peggy, Mike (John Cohen's band mate in the New Lost City Ramblers), and half brother, Pete. Cohen and Seeger had two children, Sonya (1965-2015) and Rufus.
Cohen's fascination with Appalachian and Andean culture inspired him to take many collecting trips to the Southern U.S. and to Peru, where he recorded, photographed, and produced films that presented the people and traditions in their cultural contexts. His work reflected his artistic sense and aesthetic. Cohen was a prolific documentary filmmaker, ultimately creating seventeen films through the course of his career, including The High Lonesome Sound, The End of an Old Song, Q'eros: The Shape of Survival, Mountain Music of Peru, and Visions of Mary Frank. Cohen also produced, compiled, and wrote liner notes for recordings of Appalachian music, such as An Untamed Sense of Control, High Atmosphere: Ballads and Banjo Tunes from Virginia and North Carolina, Dark Holler, and Back Roads to Cold Mountain.
Cohen guest lectured at several colleges beginning in 1968, before becoming the Area Head in photography at the State University of New York at Purchase from 1972 to 1997. There he taught courses on photography, drawing, and film. His photographs have been exhibited at galleries and museums across the United States and in Peru and England. The There Is No Eye exhibit of Cohen's photographs, organized by the Photographic Resource Center in Boston, MA, traveled to 11 museums and yielded a book of photographs and a Smithsonian Folkways album, There Is No Eye: Music for Photographs. Cohen's photographs have been published in numerous curated books, and in periodicals. Cohen died in 2019.
Scope and Content
Collection of manuscripts, sound recordings, graphic images, and moving images created and collected by John Cohen. The materials document Cohen's parallel careers as a musician (member of the New Lost City Ramblers) and writer during the 1960s American folk music revival, and his celebrated work as a documentary photographer and filmmaker, producer, and artist from the 1950s to the present. Includes interviews made by Cohen with John Hartford, Harry Smith, Roger McGuinn, Pete Seeger, Bob Dylan, Gary Davis, John Summers, Cousin Emmy, Roscoe Holcomb, Charlie Higgins, Wade Ward, Friends of Old Time Music, High Atmosphere, and photographs of these and others including E. C. Ball, Clancy Brothers, Elizabeth Cotten, Willie Dixon, Jack Elliott, Woody Guthrie, Mary Frank, Lilly Brothers, Alan Lomax, Bill Monroe, Earl Scruggs, Mike Seeger, Stanley Brothers, Belle Stewart, Stony Mountain Boys, Merle Travis, Muddy Waters, Doc Watson and many others. The collection includes documentation of Greenwich Village and Harlem, New York City; Cohen's travels to Paris and Spain in the 1950s; and later to England, Wales, Scotland, Germany, Italy and Japan, and other countries. Notable is his research for his master's thesis on Peruvian textile weaving, and subsequent fieldwork in Peru. Cohen visited Peru eight times between 1956 and 2005. Subsequent projects in Peru incorporated sound recordings of Andean music, and films as well as books about weaving, music, festivals, and dance. The majority of Cohen's Peru photographs were taken during his first three trips there and focus primarily on indigenous Andean people in the Q'ero region.
Arrangement
The John Cohen collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1. Manuscripts
Series 2. Sound recordings and moving images
Series 3. Still images
Series 4. Accrual from January 2020
Series 1-3 were arranged and described according to format, such as manuscripts and sound recordings. Series 4 was processed separately, and is mostly arranged topically, by Cohen's area of interest, such as Peru and Southern U.S. music, but there is also a large subseries that documents the administrative side of Cohen's teaching, writing, photography, and film making career. Sound recordings that do not fit into the topical subseries of Series 4 have been moved to "Series 2. Subseries 4. Sound recordings and moving image materials from 2020 accrual." Materials within the Series 4 subseries are arranged alphabetically except for the "Original Artwork" subseries, which is arranged chronologically.
Headings in titles, such as "New Lost City Ramblers" and "Hidden Threads of Peru," were provided to uphold the collection's original order according to the topics of Cohen's projects and endeavors.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Cohen, John, 1932-2019; Cohen, John, 1932-2019.; Guthrie, Woody, 1912-1967--Photographs.; Lomax, Alan, 1915-2002--Photographs.; Paley, Tom; Schwarz, Tracy; Seeger, Mike, 1933-2009; Seeger, Penny, 1943-1993.
Organizations
Down Hill Strugglers (Musical group); Friends of Old-Time Music.; New Lost City Ramblers.
Subjects
Ballads.; Beats (Persons)--Photographs.; Bluegrass musicians--Photographs.; Carnival--Peru--Quero (Cuzco); Folk festivals--United States.; Folk festivals.; Folk music festivals.; Folk music--United States.; Folk music.; Folk singers--Interviews.; Folk singers--Photographs.; Huaynos--Peru--Music.; Inca architecture--Andes Region.; Old-time music.; Quero Indians--Photographs.; Quero Indians--Social life and customs.; Quero textile fabrics--Peru--Quero (Cuzco); String band music--United States.
Places
New York (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Documentary films.; Documentary photographs.; Field notes.; Interviews.; Photographs.; Portrait photographs.; Sound recordings.
Container List
- Series 1. Manuscripts, ca. 1956-2009
  Manuscript materials related to John Cohen's film projects, musical career, photography, and writing. Includes materials related to the production of Cohen's films, correspondence, ephemera related to the New Lost City Ramblers, writings for liner notes and articles, and interview transcripts.
  - Subseries 1. Film-related materials and documentation, 1958-1999
    Manuscript materials related to Cohen's film projects. Includes royalty statements, transcriptions, and translations. Materials provide evidence of business transactions and artistic decisions made throughout the production and distribution of Cohen's films.
    - Peru films: narrations, 1978-1992, 1 folder (Box-folder 1/1)
      Narration transcriptions relating to various films, such as The Mountain Music of Peru,, Dancing with the Incas, and Carnival in Q'eros.
    - Dancing with the Incas, 1990-1993, 1 folder (Box-folder 1/2)
      Correspondence, invoices, and publicity materials relating to the film, Dancing with the Incas.
    - Record contracts, 1992-1999, 1 folder (Box-folder 1/3)
      Record contracts, correspondence and royalty statements from Smithsonian Folkways related to New Lost City Ramblers recordings and other Cohen publications on the label ( Mountain Music of Kentucky and Mountain Music of Peru ).
    - Film and television contracts, 1979-1996, 1 folder (Box-folder 1/4)
      Contracts, releases, and correspondence with film and television companies relating to various films and programs by Cohen.
    - Mystic Fire video/contract, Q'eros: The Shape of Survival, 1993-1996, 1 folder (Box-folder 1/5)
      Licenses, royalty statements, publicity materials, and correspondence relating to the film, Q'eros: The Shape of Survival.
    - University of California Media Extension: Carnival in Qeros, 1991-1999, 3 folders (Box-folder 1/6-8)
      Royalty statements, income reports, and correspondence related to the distribution of the film, Carnival in Q'eros, as well as other of Cohen's films.
    - Film contracts, various, 1986, 1988, 1992, 1 folder (Box-folder 2/9)
      Correspondence, contracts, and narration transcriptions for Cohen's films.
    - First Run/Icarus Films, 1988-1992, 1 folder (Box-folder 2/10)
      Royalty statements, publicity materials, and correspondence with Icarus Films for Pericles in America, and other of Cohen's films.
    - Cinema Guild royalties, 1985-1993, 1 folder (Box-folder 2/11)
      Royalty statements, distribution receipts, invoices, and correspondence with the Cinema Guild.
    - Film festivals, 1976, 1981-1997, 1 folder (Box-folder 18/221)
      Royalty statements, awards, grant proposals, correspondence regarding Cohen's films Mountain Music of Peru and Q'eros: the Shape of Survival.
    - Film festivals, 1976, 1981-1997, 1 folder (Box-folder 2/12)
      Royalty statements, awards, grant proposals, correspondence regarding Cohen's films.
    - Kentucky movie: High Lonesome Sound, 1961-1984, 3 folders (Box-folder 2/13-15)
      Correspondence, programs, royalty statements, contracts, notes posters, awards, invoices, lists of equipment purchased, and 1 narration transcript relating to the film The High Lonesome Sound, and The End of an Old Song. Includes equipment purchases/loans with Al Maysels (Maysels Film, Inc.).
    - Kentucky movie: High Lonesome Sound, 1961-1984, 1 folder (Box-folder 18/222)
      Correspondence, programs, royalty statements, contracts, notes posters, awards, invoices, lists of equipment purchased, and 1 narration transcript relating to the film, The High Lonesome Sound, and The End of an Old Song.
    - Kentucky movie: High Lonesome Sound, 1961-1984, 1 folder (Box-folder 21/291)
    - Hold Out Music, 1971-1977, 1982-1984, 1 folder (Box-folder 2/16)
      Royalty statements, correspondence, grant proposals, notes, posters, and ephemera relating to the film Hold Out Music, or Musical Holdouts. Includes James Monroe's 3rd Annual Bluegrass Festival schedule, as well as posters for the 3rd Annual Old Time Fiddlers and Bluegrass Convention (June, 1973) and for Sweetsmill Folk Life Camp.
    - Hold Out Music, 1971-1977, 1982-1984, 1 folder (Box-folder 18/223)
      Royalty statements, correspondence, grant proposals, notes, posters, and ephemera relating to the film "Hold Out Music," or Musical Holdouts. Includes James Monroe's 3rd Annual Bluegrass Festival schedule, as well as posters for the 3rd Annual Old Time Fiddlers and Bluegrass Convention (June, 1973) and for Sweetsmill Folk Life Camp.
    - Q'eros, copyright agreements, 1981, 1 folder (Box-folder 2/17)
      Narration transcriptions relating to various films, such as The Mountain Music of Peru, Dancing with the Incas, and Carnival in Q'eros.
    - Putnam County Film, 1970-1974, 2 folders (Box-folder 2/18, 3/19)
      Notes, grant information, correspondence, invoices for equipment, and newspaper clippings related to the making of the film, Fifty Miles From Times Square.
    - Putnam County Film, 1970-1974, 1 folder (Box-folder 18/224)
    - "Fifty Miles" Vaughn Ward Student Reports, 1970, 1 folder (Box-folder 3/20)
      Correspondence, questionnaires, and student reports relating to the film, Fifty Miles from Times Square.
    - TCB film contracts, 1972-1975, 1 folder (Box-folder 3/21)
      Correspondence, contracts, and earnings and royalty statements with T.C.B Releasing Limited (London, England) relating to the distribution of various Cohen films.
    - End of an Old Song: bills and notebooks, 1967-1982, 1984-1985, 3 folders (Box-folder 3/22-24)
      Royalty statements, contracts, distribution reports, correspondence, publicity materials, transcriptions, and notebooks relating to the film, The End of an Old Song. Includes correspondence with Bruce Jackson, Toshi Seeger, as well as equipment purchases/loans with Leacock Pennebaker.
    - End of an Old Song: bills and notebooks, 1967-1982, 1984-1985, 1 folder (Box-folder 18/225)
      Royalty statements, contracts, correspondence, publicity materials, transcriptions, and notebooks relating to the film, The End of an Old Song.
    - End of an Old Song: bills and notebooks, 1967-1982, 1984-1985, 1 folder (Box-folder 21/292)
      Includes a poster relating to the film, The End of an Old Song.
    - Hold Out Music: business, 1973-1976, 1978-1981, 1984, 2 folders (Box-folder 3/25-26)
      Contracts, correspondence, invoices for equipment, travel documents, royalty statements, 1 poster, filming logs, notes and ephemera relating to the film Hold Out Music (also known as Musical Holdouts ).
    - Cajun film project, 1969-1971, 1 folder (Box-folder 4/27)
      Notes, correspondence, grant proposal and related material, and account books relating to a proposed film about Cajun music and life.
    - Q'eros: The Shape of Survival: Films Inc. statements, 1980-1985, 1 folder (Box-folder 4/28)
      Royalty statements, correspondence, and invoices related to the making of the film, Q'eros: The Shape of Survival.
    - Films Inc. statement, 1989, 1 folder (Box-folder 4/29)
      Royalty statement for The End of an Old Song and The High Lonesome Sound.
    - Billie Jean Isbell, Ed M. Franquemont and Christine Franquemont, 1984, 1 folder (Box-folder 4/30)
      Drafts of essays, including "The Unfolding of Symmetries: The Structuring of Andean Cloth."
    - Textile Texts, Chris and Ed Franquemont, ca. 1984, 1 folder (Box-folder 4/31)
      Drafts and correspondence related to Andean textiles.
    - Lima music, undated, 1 folder (Box-folder 4/32)
      Articles, notes, and song transcriptions.
    - Huaylas, undated, 1 folder (Box-folder 4/33)
      1 draft by Paul Daughty, "The Fiest of St. Elizabeth: A Ceremonial Expression of Communitas in Huaylas, Peru."
    - Xeroxed articles: important sources, 1981-1992, 3 folders (Box-folder 4/34-36)
      Articles from magazines and academic journals about Andean music, popular culture in Peru, and Indian languages in Peru.
    - Becky Harclerode translations, 1988-1992, 1 folder (Box-folder 5/37)
      Interview transcripts and song transcriptions done in Peru as part of the Huayno project.
    - Early Peru recordings, 1992, 1 folder (Box-folder 5/38)
      Correspondence, liner notes, and record catalogs of Peruvian music on Victor and other labels.
    - Interview: Pastorcita Huaracina - Floresnillo Flores, 1989, 1 folder (Box-folder 5/39)
      Interview transcript and correspondence with Floresnillo Flores who worked at the Workers' Sindicate of Folkloric Artosts in Peru.
    - Interview: Pastorcita Huaracina - Jaime Guardia, 1989, 1 folder (Box-folder 5/40)
      Interview transcripts and correspondence.
    - Interview: Maximo Ledesma; Discos Puquio; La Musica en Parinacoches y Lucanas, 1989, 1 folder (Box-folder 5/41)
      Interview transcripts.
    - Interview with Leo Casas, 1991, 1 folder (Box-folder 5/42)
      Interview transcript and correspondence related to Huayno music.
    - Interview: Director School of Folklore, Lima; Maximo Alana, Syndicate Folklore Arts; Maximo Damian, Scissor Dance violinist, 1989-1990, 1 folder (Box-folder 5/43)
    - Spanish versions interview: Discos del Puerto; Maximo Alanya, Union; Jaime Guamola; Maximo Damian, 1989, 1 folder (Box-folder 5/44)
      Interview transcripts in Spanish and correspondence.
    - Map of Peru, 1958, 1 folder (Box-folder 5/45)
      1 map of Peru published by Esso petroleum.
    - Film narration - Mountain Music of Peru, 1984, 1 folder (Box-folder 5/46)
      Narration scripts, titles, subtitles, and notes relating to the film, Mountain Music of Peru.
    - Film narration - Mountain Music of Peru, 1984, 1 folder (Box-folder 18/226)
    - Cuzco/Charango, undated, 1 folder (Box-folder 5/47)
      Narration script and subtitles.
    - Scissors Tijeras (Scissor Dance)/Maximo, 1979-1984, 1 folder (Box-folder 5/48)
      Notes, ephemera, 1 book, and correspondence. Book is titled, El Violin de Isua: Biografia de un Interprete de Musica Folklorica.
    - Puno/Titicaca, 1979-1984, 1 folder (Box-folder 5/49)
      Ephemera, articles about the region in Peru.
    - Choquela, 1984, 1986-1987, 1 folder (Box-folder 5/50)
      Prints, notes, articles, publicity materials, ephemera, correspondence, interview transcripts, song transcriptions, and sample poster layout relating to the film, Choquela: Only Interpretation.
    - Choquela, 1984, 1986-1987, 1 folder (Box-folder 6/51)
    - Choquela, 1984, 1986-1987, 2 folders (Box-folder 18/227-228)
    - Steven Webster, 1973-1986, 2 folders (Box-folder 6/52-53)
      Working papers and correspondence with Steven Webster of the University of Auckland Department of Anthropology on Andean pastoralism.
    - Textile Network, Peabody Museum, 1985, 1 folder (Box-folder 6/54)